Arrival  降臨
字幕由SSK字幕組傾情譯制
字幕僅供學習，勿用於商
轉載請註明出處，版權歸片方所有
新浪微博@SSK字幕組
官網：www.sskzmz.com
我曾經認為
I used to think
這是你的故事的開始
this was the beginning of your story.
SSK字幕組
回憶是一種奇怪的東西
Memory is a strange thing.
因為它和我所想的不太一樣
It doesn't work like I thought it did.
我們太局限於時間 因果順序
We are so bound by time, by its order.
好
Okay.
好 來我這兒
Okay. Come back to me.
讓媽媽抱抱
Come back to me.
把手舉起來
Stick 'em up!
你就是鎮上的警長
Are you the sheriff in this here town?
這是我的撓癢槍 我會抓住你
These are my tickle guns, and I'm gonna getcha!
不
No!
你想讓我追你 你最好得跑了
You want me to chase you? You better run!
-啊 -哦
- Ah! - Oh!
我還記得中間的一些片段
I remember moments in the middle.
我愛你
I love you.
我恨你
I hate you!
到這裏就結束了
And this was the end.
噓
Shhh...
到媽媽這裏來
Come back to me.
回到媽媽這裏
You come back to me.
可現在我不確定
But now I'm not so sure
我還能不能分得清起點和終點了
I believe in beginnings and endings.
有那麼一段你生命之外的時間 勾勒出你的故事
There are days that define your story beyond your life.
就像它們降臨的那天
Like the day they arrived.
早上好
Good morning.
Morning.
大家都去哪了
Where is everyone?
好吧 那咱們開始上課
Okay. Well, let's get started.
今天我們來講葡萄牙語
Today we are talking about Portuguese
以及其為什麼聽起來和
and why it sounds so different
其他的羅馬語系那麼不同
from the other Romance languages.
葡萄牙語起源於加利西亞王國
The story of Portuguese begins in the kingdom of Galicia...
-抱歉 -在中世紀的時候
- Sorry. - ...in the Middle Ages,
語言被視作為對藝術的一種表達
where language was seen as an expression of art.
有什麼想分享的新聞嗎
Any news you want to share?
班克斯博士 您能打開電視看新聞台嗎
Dr. Banks, can you turn the TV to a news channel?
警察已經在該處周邊區域
...but police have already set up a blockade
設置了封鎖
here around the area.
如你所見 我們盡了最大可能走近
As you can see, we've got just about as close as we can,
但不幸的是
but unfortunately,
蒙大拿現在是完全封鎖的狀態
Montana right now is on complete lockdown.
該物體是在40分鐘前著陸於
The object apparently touched down 40 minutes ago,
94號州際公路的北側
just north of I-94.
我們在這裏等候消息
We're waiting to hear if this is perhaps
看看這是不是一艘實驗飛船或是
an experimental vessel or...
稍等
Hold on, it...
我剛剛得知還有更多像這樣的物體
I'm learning that more objects like this have landed in
降落在世界上
as many as eight other locations
多達八個其他的位置
around the world.
是的 我們能
Yes, can we?
這是來自北海道的畫面
This is from a site in Hokkaido.
這是正在發生的 全球性事件
This is worldwide. It is happening right now.
好吧 呃
Okay. Um...
抱歉 下課吧
I'm sorry. Class is dismissed.
你個笨蛋 直著往我這開
You are an idiot! You drove right into me!
你把我車都撞壞了
You just ruined my car!
現在 在當局對該物體進行評估時
For now, we're simply asking for cooperation
我們只希望大家能夠配合
while authorities assess the object.
那你的意思是說這不是我們國家的
So, you're saying it's not ours?
你知道它是否來自地球嗎
Do you even know if it's from Earth?
我們目前還在搜集信息
We 're still collecting information.
還有與其他國家進行協調
We're coordinating with other countries.
我們不是唯一一個在境內出現
We're not the only ones to
這麼個東西的國家
have one of these in our backyard.
如果這是某種和平的第一類接觸
If this is some sort of peaceful first contact,
為什麼發來12個
why send 12?
為什麼不就派一艘來
Why not just one?
是啊 我知道 我看到那個了
Yeah, I know. I saw that, too.
嗯
Uh-huh.
嗯 媽我不知道
Uh-huh. I don't know, Mom.
我和您看的是一樣的新聞
I'm watching the same news coverage you are.
行了 媽 您別理那些電視台
Well, Mom, please don't bother with that channel.
我跟您說過多少次了 那些人都是笨蛋
How many times do I have to tell you? Those people are idiots.
是啊 行了 我聽起來緊張嗎
Yeah, well, do I sound nervous?
是 可不嘛
Okay. Exactly. So...
我 是啊 您懂我的
Um, me? Yeah, um, you know me.
還那麼回事
I'm about the same.
媽 我挺好的
Mom, I'm fine.
好啦 我會再給您打的 再見
Okay, I'll call you later. Bye.
從降臨到現在大約八小時
And around eight hours after landing,
目前還沒有任何被稱為第一類接觸
there are still no signs of what might be called
的跡象
"First contact."
現在 物體至少有一千五百英尺高
Now, the objects measure at least 1,500 feet tall...
報告稱有兩個物體進入俄羅斯領空
Two are reported to have penetrated Russian airspace.
一個在西伯利亞 另一個在黑海沿岸的
One in Siberia, and the other off the coast of the Black...
海洋上面
...above the ocean.
目前 共有十二個不明物體
So far, there are 12 unidentified objects
分佈全球
spread across the globe.
從其位置上來看並無邏輯
There is no obvious logic to their locations
沒有證據表明這些飛船正在運行
and no evidence that the ships are even occu...
有這種考慮 即這可能是一種
...entertain the idea that if it is a kind of vessel,
無人駕駛的飛船
it may be unmanned.
無論如何 我們有應對此類事態的預案
Regardless, we have a protocol for scenarios like this.
委內瑞拉 正在直播
在星期二的特別事件之後
After Tuesday's extraordinary events,
總統今晨宣佈進入緊急狀態
the President this morning has declared a state of emergency,
僅在蒙大拿州就部署了
with as many as 5,000 National Guard
有五千名國民警衛隊
being deployed to the state of Montana alone.
邊境被封鎖 航班被停飛
Borders are closed and flights have been grounded,
有上百萬的遊客被滯留
stranding millions of travelers.
人們瘋狂搶購汽油 水和食物
Panic buying of gas, water and food
事態持續擴大
continues to escalate,
聯邦政府暫時解除了
and federal authorities have temporarily lifted
對執法部門的所有加班禁令
all caps on overtime for law enforcement.
煙酒槍械管理局已經暫時停止發放新的持槍許可
The ATF has put a temporary ban on new gun licenses,
迫使許多的狩獵設備和武器
forcing many independent suppliers of
的獨立供應商不得不
hunting equipment and firearms
暫停對公眾開放
to close their doors to the public.
已經四十八小時過去了 在十二個不明飛行的降落地
Forty-eight hours later and no further development...
兩天了
Two days...
還沒有任何進展
...from the site of the 12 UFOs.
公眾已經在期待我們
...and already, the public expects us
來瞭解答案
to know the answers.
我是韋伯上校
I'm Colonel G.T. Weber.
我們從未正式見過面
We never formally met,
不過兩年前 你為軍方情報部做過
but two years ago, you did some Farsi translations
波斯語的翻譯
for Army Intelligence.
哦
Oh.
你對那些叛亂者的視頻翻譯的效率挺高的
You made quick work of those insurgent videos.
你對叛亂者的處理效率也挺高的
You made quick work of those insurgents.
凡是涉及到翻譯
You are on the top of everyone's list
你是公認最頂尖的
when it comes to translations.
你的單一範圍背景調查還有兩年的權限
And you have another two years in your SSBI,
所以你仍有接觸最高機密的許可
so you still have top-secret clearance.
這就是為什麼我會出現在你的辦公室裏 而不是在伯克利
That's why I'm in your office and not at Berkeley.
好吧
Okay.
我想請你翻譯些東西
I have something I need you to translate for me.
你們為什麼來這裏
Why are you here?
你們 你們能理解我們的語言嗎
Can you... Can you understand us?
你們從哪裏來
Where did you come from?
現在你聽過了 你有什麼想法嗎
Now you heard it. What do you make of it?
那就是
Is that...
是的
Yes.
有多少
How many?
-什麼有多少 -有多少在說話
- How many what? - Um, how many, um, speaking?
兩個
Two.
假設它們不是同時在說話
Assume they were not speaking at the same time.
你確定嗎 它們有嘴嗎
Are you sure? Did they have mouths...
你要是翻譯這個的話 你怎麼做
How would you approach translating this?
你有沒有聽到什麼詞彙 短語
Do you hear any words? Phrases?
我不 我不知道
I don't... I don't know.
那你能告訴我什麼嗎
So what can you tell me?
我能說的就是不可能僅根據音頻文件
I can tell you that it's impossible
來翻譯這些
to translate from an audio file.
我得親自到現場 跟它們進行互動
I would need to be there, to interact with them.
做波斯語翻譯的時候你也沒互動啊
You didn't need that with the Farsi translations.
我不需要是因為我會波斯語
I didn't need it because I already knew the language,
但是這個 這是 呃
but this... This is... Ah...
我知道你想幹什麼
I know what you're doing.
-那你說說我在要幹嘛 -我是不會帶你去蒙大拿的
- Tell me what I'm doing. - I'm not taking you to Montana.
我不能讓別人把最高機密許可
It's all I can do to keep it from turning into a tourist site
當成旅遊景點的門票
for everybody who has a TS clearance.
我只是告訴你完成這項工作
I'm just telling you what it would take
需要什麼
to do this job.
我不是來商量的
This is not a negotiation.
如果我離開這裏 你就沒機會了
If I leave here, your chance is gone.
再見
Good day.
上校
Colonel?
你剛才說伯克利
You mentioned Berkeley.
接下來你是不是要去詢問丹佛斯
Are you going to ask Danvers next?
可能吧
Maybe.
在你讓他工作之前
Before you commit to him,
問問他梵文裏戰爭一詞及其翻譯
ask him the Sanskrit word for war and its translation.
在今晚的中國和俄羅斯在聯合國加入磋商後
An agreement on sharing scientific discoveries
有望達成
looks closer tonight,
一個科學發現共享協議
as Russia and China join talks at the United Nations.
與此同時 世界範圍內的金融市場處於危機中
Meanwhile, financial markets across the world are in crisis
道瓊斯工業指數下跌
as the Dow Jones Industrial Average fell
超過兩千點
over 2,000 points...
早上好
Morning.
上校
Colonel?
伽維斯提
Gavisti.
他說這表示「爭論」
He says it means "An argument."
你覺得那個詞是什麼意思
What do you say it means?
渴望更多的牛
A desire for more cows.
裝好你的行李
Pack your bags.
-好吧 給我二十分鐘 -十分鐘後起飛
- All right. Give me 20 minutes? - Takeoff in ten.
班克斯博士 這邊請
Dr. Banks. Right this way, please.
收到 準備前往
Contact and ready to approach...
抱歉 班克斯博士 我來檢查一下你的安全帶
Excuse me, Dr. Banks, let me make sure you're properly secured.
你還好嗎
You okay?
對不起 我剛才沒聽見你在說什麼
Sorry, I couldn't hear what you were saying.
「語言」是文明的基石
"Language is the foundation of civilization.
它是將人們聯結在一起的膠水
"It is the glue that holds a people together.
它是在衝突中最先使用的武器
"It is the first weapon drawn in a conflict."
露易絲 這是伊恩·唐納利 露易絲·班克斯 伊恩·唐納利
Louise, this is Ian Donnelly. Louise Banks, Ian Donnelly.
這就是打過招呼了
That's quite a greeting.
是啊 你寫的這個
Yeah, well, you wrote it.
嗯
Yeah.
這就是你寫來做序言的東西
It's the kind of thing you write as a preface.
博得讀者眼球
Dazzle them with the basics.
是 挺好的 即便是錯的
Yeah, it's great. Even if it's wrong.
錯了
It's wrong?
嗯 文明的基石不是語言
Well, the cornerstone of civilization isn't language,
而是科學
it's science.
伊恩是來自阿拉莫斯國家實驗室的理論物理學家
Ian is a theoretical physicist from Los Alamos.
你向我匯報 但當你在殼裏時
You'll be reporting to me, but you'll be working with him
你和他一起共事
when you're in the shell.
它們管那個不明飛行物叫殼
That's what they're calling the UFO.
首要目的 它們從何來 何所求
Priority one: what do they want and where are they from?
除此以外 它們是怎麼來到這裏的
And beyond that, how did they get here?
它們能進行超光速旅行嗎
Are they capable of faster-than-light travel?
我準備了一系列的問題要問
I've prepared a list of questions to go over,
以二進制序列的「握手」為開始
starting with a series of "Handshake" Binary sequences...
我們能不能在向它們問數學題之前
How about we just talk to them
先跟它們交流起來
before we start throwing math problems at them?
這就是為什麼同時請了你們倆
This is why you're both here.
我來端咖啡
I'll bring the coffee.
與外星人一起喝咖啡
Coffee with some aliens.
你帶他們兩個去凱特勒博士那裏去
I want you to take these two to Dr. Kettler.
遵命 長官
Yes, sir.
請跟著這位上尉去醫務室
Follow the captain to medical.
這只需要幾分鐘就好
It should take just a few minutes,
然後我們就開始
and then we'll get started.
把背包交給我們 請把手機交給我
We'll take care of your bag. I'll take your cell phones.
手機拿出來
Cell phones!
跟著我
Follow me.
把這些穿上 你們得一直穿著它們
Put these on. You're gonna wear them at all times.
長官 他們到了
Sir, they're here.
露易絲·班克斯 伊恩·唐納利
Louise Banks? Ian Donnelly?
你們上一頓飯什麼時候吃的
When was the last time either of you have eaten?
-昨晚 -我也是
- Last night. - Same.
上一次在壓力狀態下做事
Last time you did something stressful?
現在算嗎
Does now count?
開個玩笑
Just saying...
哦 被抬進救傷直升機的是誰
Uh, who was being carted off in the medevac?
不是所有人都可以經受住這樣的經歷的
Not everyone is able to process experiences like this.
我需要抽一些你的血
I'm gonna get some blood from you
然後給你打一針疫苗
and give you an immunization dose
能抵禦多種細菌威脅
that covers a battery of bacterial threats.
請你在這裏簽個字 把袖子擼上去
Could you sign these, please? And roll up your sleeves.
你們誰有幽閉恐懼癥
Either of you claustrophobic?
-沒有 -沒有
- No. - No.
目前有沒有在用藥 對什麼過敏
Currently taking any medications? Allergies?
有懷孕嗎
Pregnant?
沒有
No.
加強劑會對你的身體系統產生衝擊
The booster is a kick to your system,
所以你會感覺到一些副作用
so you may experience some side effects,
比如噁心 頭暈 頭疼
nausea, dizziness, headaches,
耳鳴之類的
a ringing in your ears, like you have tinnitus.
他們不管怎樣都不離開
They wouldn't go, either way.
你看到他怎麼了嗎
You see what's happening to him?
這到底是怎麼運行的
How does this even work?
讀數沒變化
The readings do not change,
但 我不懂
but I don't know,
就好像我們是一片紙上的蟲子
it's like we're insects on a piece of paper,
他們在讓我們自己撤退
and they're easing us out of the house.
在一百一十二分鐘十九秒後
At exactly 112 minutes and 19 seconds,
重力開始起變化 讓我們滑出房間
gravity starts to shift and slides us out of the room.
對此你有科學解釋嗎
Have you found a scientific explanation for it?
比如 這對它們來說有利
Like, is it for them?
哦 不 我覺得是為我們方便的
Uh, no. We think it's for us.
在房間內部的空氣似乎並不流通
Air doesn't seem to circulate inside the chamber,
所以兩小時後 我們的氧氣就消耗光了
so after about two hours, we run out of oxygen.
往那個房間泵送空氣用不了十八個小時
It doesn't take 18 hours to pump fresh air into a room.
大氣
Atmosphere...
你說什麼
Excuse me?
如果它們的大氣和地球上的不一樣
If their atmosphere is different from Earth,
在它們每次打開艙門之前
it would certainly take hours
它們得將氧氣含量及氣壓進行重新調整
to rebalance their O2 content and pressure for us
已達到我們的適應範圍內
every time they open their door.
那麼你是說它們能令我們窒息 如果它們想的話
So, they could suffocate us if they wanted.
這位是來自中情局的哈爾彭特工
This is Agent Halpern with the CIA.
我帶你們去你們的工位
Let me get you two to your stations.
好的 長官
Yes, sir.
記住 我們得盡快得到答案
Remember, we need answers as soon as possible.
它們何所求 來自何方
What do they want? Where are they from?
以及為什麼來這裏
Why are they here?
這是首要任務
This is the priority.
大家 這位是伊恩·唐納利博士
Everyone, this is Dr. Ian Donnelly.
他負責帶領這個隊
He'll be running this team here.
它們有沒有對什麼作出反應
Have they responded to anything?
形狀 模式 數字 斐波那契數列
Shapes, patterns, numbers, Fibonacci?
當它們回復「你好」的時候
We can't tell what they're saying
我們並不知道它們在說什麼
when they respond to "Hello," So...
別太急於求成
Don't get ahead of yourself.
你們得出什麼了
What have you figured out?
我們這才剛剛開始 各位早上好
We're just getting started. Good morning!
這是露易絲·班克斯博士 她負責帶你們隊
This is Dr. Louise Banks. She'll be heading your team.
很高興見到你
It's a pleasure meeting you.
班克斯博士接手沃克博士的任務
Dr. Banks is taking over the mission from Dr. Walker.
那是一個十五分鐘警報
That's a 15-minute warning.
你以前潛過水嗎
You scuba-dive before?
我們要去的地方有哪種輻射
What kind of radiation exposure are we walking into?
就是形式上的以防萬一 為安全考慮
Nominal. These are just for safety.
那麼 有沒有和那些的肢體接觸
So, is there any physical contact with the, um...
有人和我一樣講不出「外星人」嗎
Am I the only one having trouble saying "Aliens"?
那裏有一面牆 像是玻璃牆
There's a wall. Like, a glass wall.
你碰不到它們
You can't get to them.
它們長什麼樣子
So, what do they look like?
你馬上就能看到了 加快
You'll see soon enough. Hurry up.
防護服一開始很笨重
The suits are clumsy at first,
但你會習慣的
but you get used to them.
我開第二輛車
I'll open a second vehicle.
我們幾分鐘就到
We'll be there in a few minutes.
確保你把住什麼東西
Make sure you hold on to something.
收到 禿鷹 我們會監視 但不啟動 完畢
Copy, Condor. We will observe, but not initiate. Over.
小心
Watch your step.
我們會保持阿爾法頻道暢通 完畢
We'll keep Alpha channel open. Over.
阿爾法 請注意 濕度從昨天開始增加了
Alpha, be advised. Humidity increased since yesterday.
每隔十八小時
Every 18 hours,
底部的門就會打開
the door opens up at the bottom.
這就是我們要去的地方
That's where we go in.
零移動 阿爾法可以前進 完畢
Zero movement. Alpha detail, clear to proceed. Over.
收到 禿鷹
Copy, Condor.
現在開始上升 完畢
Beginning our ascent now. Over.
十英尺
Ten feet.
五英尺
Five feet.
二 一
Two, one...
阿爾法可以進入前廳
Alpha clear to enter antechamber.
開始行動
Moving into position.
距目標三十英尺
Thirty feet from target.
防護服遙測系統正常
Suit telemetry now full strength,
但是有未知干擾
despite unknown interference.
三 二 一
Three, two, one.
氧氣含量 百分之二十點三
Oxygen level: 20.3%.
未檢測到可知毒物 完畢
No known contaminates. Over.
無線信號正在減弱
Radio signals are decreasing.
百分之九十 百分之八十五
90%, 85%...
好吧 就這樣發生了
Yeah, that just happened.
好了 我們上去吧
All right, let's move!
時不要浪費時間
Time is wasting.
你準備好了嗎 準備好了嗎
You ready? You ready?
來吧
Let's do it!
禿鷹 我和馬克斯上尉先上 完畢
Condor, I'm proceeding first with Captain Marks, over.
前廳重力微乎其微 完畢
Gravity nominal in the antechamber. Over!
一切都好 長官
It's all good, sir.
你可以上來
You can proceed.
待命 好的 上來
Stand by! Okay, bring it up.
心肺功能減弱
Vitals are low.
無線信號穩定在百分之七十五 完畢
Radio signal strength stable at 75%. Over.
你還好嗎
You okay?
還好
Yeah.
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks?
你可以的 來吧
You can do this. Come on.
我不知道 我 我認為
I don't know. I... I think...
抓住她
Grab her.
唐納利 你怎麼樣
Donnelly, are you all right?
唐納利博士 你還好嗎
Dr. Donnelly, you good?
Dr. Donnelly, are you all right?
請回答 完畢
Please respond. Over.
我還好
Yeah.
老天吶
Holy fuck!
我們要去那
We're gonna go down there,
你們開始工作
and you're gonna start your job.
-好的 -行嗎
- Okay. - Okay?
可以
Okay.
大家聽好 前進
Everybody, move out!
阿爾法準備好了
Alpha detail is in position.
團隊準備好了
Team is in position.
我們正在前進
We're on the move.
禿鷹 阿爾法到達正廳了
Condor, Alpha's now in the nave.
正在安裝設備和遙感系統 完畢
Setting up equipment and telemetry. Over.
所以 接下來怎麼辦
So, what happens now?
他們會來的
They arrive.
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks?
你可以開始了
You can start.
在氣密室中
...in airlock.
在通過氣密室門之前不要停下
Do not stop until you have passed the airlock door.
不要脫掉防護服
Do not attempt to remove hazmat suits
在沒有工作人員幫助下
without assistance from authorized personnel.
防護服
hazmat suits
在沒有工作人員的幫助下
without assistance from authorized personnel.
等一下 一分鐘 就一分鐘
Wait. Just a minute. Just a minute.
安全
Clear.
-好的 -請把腳移出來
- All right. - Step on out, please.
拿著它
Now hold that.
我被炒了嗎
Am I fired?
你比上一個好多了
You're better than the last guy.
這沒有讓我好受些
That doesn't make me feel any better.
到凌晨兩點你們還有些思考的時間
You both have till 02:00 hours to figure something out.
好的 然後呢
Okay. What happens then?
你們再去
You go back in.
十二處著陸的發現
Violence continues to spread
使得暴力在美國持續蔓延
across the US today in the wake of the 12 landings.
在國家警衛隊
The president has declared
對連續三天晚上的打砸搶
a mandatory dusk-to-dawn curfew
鎮壓失敗後
after the crackdown by the National Guard failed
總統下達了對黃昏到黎明的宵禁命令
to prevent a third night of looting across the country.
在南達科他州 一百四十四個
In North Dakota, 144 members of
聖勞倫斯五旬節派成員
the Saint Lawrence Pentecostal Cult
在點燃易燃物後死亡
are feared dead after they set their compound ablaze.
他們網站上宣稱外星人的到來
Their website claims the arrival of the aliens
說明了一個預言
set in motion a prophesy that...
我們將在十五分鐘後行動 你有什麼新信息嗎
Uh, we're up in 15. You got any new intel?
是的 我們有一些他們的聲音
Yeah, we've been playing back some of their sounds.
你們怎麼得到的
Where does that get you?
他們向我們發出了聲音
Well, they play audio back at us,
從一個看不見的地方
from an unseen source.
什麼的聲音
Audio of what?
他們在房間裏的一些交流
Uh, it's bits of conversation from the room.
隨意的對話片段
Random clips of dialogue.
說真的 我們什麼都沒得到
Really, we have nothing.
距出發十四分鐘
T-minus 14 minutes to shell access.
氧氣罐狀態
1 滿  4 滿
2 滿  5 滿
3 滿  6 滿
距出發九分鐘
T-minus 9 minutes to shell access.
那是幹什麼的
What's that for?
視覺輔助手段
A visual aid.
聽著 我永遠都不可能說他們的語言
Look, I'm never gonna be able to speak their words,
假設他們說的是種語言的話
if they are talking,
但他們可能會有一些書面語言
but they might have some sort of written language
或用於視覺交流的東西
or basis for visual communication.
好的 我們開始吧
Okay. Let's get started.
人類
Human.
"Human."
我是人類 你們呢
I'm human. What are you?
人類
Human.
我的天哪
Oh my God!
你記錄下來了嗎
Are you getting this?
是的 長官 我正把這個傳回營地
Yes, sir! It's uploading back to base camp.
露易絲 這太不可思議了
Louise, that's incredible.
人類
Human.
好的 慢一點
Okay, slow down now.
慢一點
Slow down.
我不想打擊你的成功
I don't wanna take away from your success in there,
但是 班克斯博士 這真的是正確的方法嗎
but Dr. Banks, is this really the right approach?
嘗試教給他們說和讀
Trying to teach them how to speak and read?
這要花費更長時間
That's gotta take longer.
你錯了 這更快
You're wrong. It's faster.
你在那做的每件事
Everything you do in there,
我都要給一屋子的人解釋
I have to explain to a room full of men
他們的問題都是
whose first and last question is...
這將怎樣被用來對付我們
"How can this be used against us?"
所以你要給我更多的解釋
So you're gonna have to give me more than that.
袋鼠
Kangaroo.
那是什麼
What is that?
在一七七零年
In 1770,
詹姆斯·庫克船長的船
Captain James Cook's ship ran aground
在澳大利亞海邊擱淺
off the coast of Australia,
他帶了一隊人深入
and he led a party into the country,
遇到了土著人
and they met the Aboriginal people.
一個水手指著
One of the sailors pointed at
跳來跳去
the animals that hop around
將它們的孩子放在育兒袋中的動物
and put their babies in their pouch,
問它們是什麼
and he asked what they were,
土著人回答 Kangaroo[袋鼠]
and the Aborigine said, "Kangaroo."
你想說什麼
And the point is?
沒過多久他們知道了
It wasn't till later that they learned that
Kangaroo的意思是我聽不懂 所以
"Kangaroo" Means "I don't understand." So,
我這麼做是為了我們不把那裏的事情翻譯錯
I need this so that we don't misinterpret things in there.
否則 將會花費十倍以上的時間
Otherwise, this is gonna take 10 times as long.
現在我接受你的解釋
I can sell that for now.
但是在下次進去之前
But I need you to submit your vocabulary words
我需要你上交你的詞彙
before the next session.
好的
Fair.
記住土著人所遭受的苦難
And remember what happened to the Aborigines.
一個更加高級的種族幾乎將他們趕盡殺絕
A more advanced race nearly wiped them out.
那是個好故事
It's a good story.
謝謝
Thanks.
假的
It's not true.
但它證明了我的觀點
But it proves my point.
我認為我們可以複製一些基本數字序列
We think we were able to reproduce
發回給他們
some prime number sequences back at them.
還是小有成就的
So that's something.
那麼 祝賀你 你像只鸚鵡
Well, congratulations. You're a parrot.
比那難多了 你個混蛋
It's a lot more than that, you cheeky bastard,
你沒看到嗎
don't you see?
他們似乎不懂我們的代數
They can't seem to follow our algebra,
但是複雜的行為 他們懂
but complex behaviors, that clicks.
這根本說不通 不是嗎
Well that doesn't make any sense at all, does it?
問題是 不是每個人都理解我們
Problem is, not everyone shares our policy
中國呼籲謹慎行事 在上海聚集武裝力量
向外星人的開放態度
of being open with the aliens.
你見過尚將軍嗎
Have you met General Shang?
他的命令就像多米諾骨牌
The call sign for him is Big Domino.
不管尚將軍幹什麼
Whatever Shang does,
至少有四個國家會跟隨他
at least four other nations will follow.
露易絲 我們今天要上去
Louise? We have to gain ground today.
好的
Okay.
-你的詞彙表呢 -在這
- You have a vocabulary list for me? - I do.
你準備教他們你和伊恩的名字
You're gonna teach them your name and Ian's?
是的 這樣我們就能知道他們的名字了
Yes, so that we can learn
如果他們有名字的話
their names if they have names,
然後教給他們代詞
and then introduce pronouns later.
這些都是小學單詞
These are all grade-school words:
吃 走
eat, walk.
解釋一下
Help me understand.
好的
Okay. Um...
噢 不不不 別擦上邊
Oh, no, no, no! Not the top!
好的 這是你想知道的 對嗎
Okay, this is where you wanna get to, right?
你們來地球的目的是什麼？
-是的 -好的
- That is the question. - Okay.
所以 首先我們需要確保
So, first, we need to make sure that
他們知道什麼是問題
they understand what a question is.
那麼 問題的本質就是
Okay, the nature of a request for information
帶有答案的信息
along with a response.
接著 我們需要讓他們分清
Then, we need to clarify the difference between
個體的你和集體的你
a specific "You" And a collective "You,"
因為我們不想知道為什麼其中的一個人來了
because we don't wanna know why Joe Alien is here,
我們想知道的是為什麼他們全都來了
we want to know why they all landed.
理解「目的」需要引入「意圖」這個概念
And purpose requires an understanding of intent.
我們需要搞清楚
We need to find out:
他們能做有意識的決定嗎
do they make conscious choices?
或者說他們的動機是本能的
Or is their motivation so instinctive
他們並不能理解什麼是問題
that they don't understand a "Why" Question at all?
最重要的是
And... And biggest of all,
我們需要和他們有足夠多的詞彙
we need to have enough vocabulary with them
以便理解他們的答案
that we understand their answer.
我明白了
I get it.
按照你的詞彙表來
Stick to your list.
只是
Just
不要增加任何東西
don't add anything to it.
...是二點九七
...are at 2.97.
氧氣含量 百分之二十一點四 完畢
Oxygen level: 21.4%. Over.
禿鷹 阿爾法現在在中廳
Condor, Alpha's now in the nave.
設置好裝備和遙感系統 完畢
Setting up equipment and telemetry. Over.
我們開始吧
Let's get started.
露易絲 露易絲 我是露易絲
Louise. Louise. I am Louise.
那是什麼
What is that?
那是一個新符號嗎 我看不懂
Is that a new symbol? I can't tell.
我不知道 我認為那還是人類的意思
I don't know. I think it's the symbol for human again.
他只是在尾部加了一點彎曲
It just has a little curl on the end,
可能是問句的意思
maybe to indicate a question.
我不知道
I don't know.
我不知道 露易絲
I don't know, Louise.
我認為他們很疑惑
I think they're getting confused.
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks,
你可以進行下一個單詞了
perhaps we should move on to the next word.
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks!
我沒事
It's okay.
發生了什麼
What's going on?
嘿 你在幹嘛呢
Hey! What are you doing?
沒事 我很好
Yeah, I'm fine.
你瘋了嗎
Are you insane?
他們需要看清我
They need to see me.
她把防護服脫了
She's taking off her hazmat suit.
這可以嗎
Is it okay?
你有被感染的危險
You're risking contamination.
他們需要看請我
They need to see me.
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks...
Dr. Banks.
她向屏幕走去了
She's walking towards the screen.
我們要中止任務嗎
Should we abort?
請求收到 等待後續命令
Recourse noted. Stand by for further orders.
回到自己的位置上去
Go back to your stations.
這才是合適的自我介紹 嘿
Now that's a proper introduction. Hey.
露易絲
Louise.
我是露易絲
I am Louise.
伊恩 你想介紹下你自己嗎
Ian, do you want to introduce yourself?
好
Uh, yeah.
露易絲
Louise.
管它呢
Screw it!
每個人都會死 對嗎
Everybody dies, right?
長官 唐納利脫掉了防護服
Sir, Donnelly is taking off his hazmat suit.
請求中止
Permission to abort?
繼續
Continue the session.
伊恩
Ian.
露易絲
Louise.
你們
You...
你們呢
Who are you?
我認為這是他們的名字
I think those are their names.
它們有名字
They have names.
所以 我們要叫他們什麼呢
So, what are we gonna call them?
我不知道
I don't know.
艾伯特和科斯特洛怎麼樣
I was thinking Abbott and Costello.
可以
Yeah.
-可以嗎 -是的 我喜歡
- Yeah? - Yeah, I like it.
我喜歡
I like it.
哇哦
Wow!
一隊 下車
Team 1, exit your vehicle
直接去消毒營
and proceed directly ahead to the decontamination tent.
開著呼吸器直到進入儀器室
Leave your respirator on until you reach the equipment room.
我知道 噓
I know. Shhh!
二隊 下車
Team 2, exit your vehicles
去消毒營
and continue to the decontamination tent.
開著呼吸機
Leave your respirators on
在到達儀器室之前
and do not hesitate
不要停下
until you have reached the equipment room.
感覺怎麼樣
How do you feel?
精疲力竭
Overworked.
我猜不需要我告訴你
Well, I guess I don't need to tell you
你把自己置於危險之中
you're putting yourself at risk.
還沒有發現有毒放射物
There's no signs of radiation poisoning yet.
看看你的血液檢測情況
We'll see how your blood tests look.
現在 我要給你另一種藥
For now, I'm gonna give you another boost.
好的
Okay.
沒有放射物
No radiation.
也沒有檢測到其他物質
Nothing else we can detect either,
但我還是要給他們打一針混合疫苗
but I'd give them a strong cocktail, regardless.
這是我們第一次取得這麼大的進步
It's the first time we've made significant progress.
好吧 這風險我們擔了
All right. We'll take the risk.
好了 親愛的
Okay, honey...
那裏發生了什麼
What is going on there?
親愛的
Honey...
告訴我
Just tell me!
你不需要擔心 好嗎
You don't need to worry, okay?
-我怎麼能不擔心 -冷靜點
- How can I not worry? - Just calm down.
冷靜下來
Just calm down.
貝基問我怪獸會不會把爸爸殺了
Becky asked me if the monsters are going to kill Daddy!
親愛的 這不會發生的
Honey, it's not gonna happen.
你要好好的
Just stay safe.
你不需要擔心
You don't need to worry.
求你了 我好害怕
Please! I'm so scared!
所有低級別外國語言學研究者
All junior xenolinguistics
和科學人員一定要遵守
and science personnel must observe
全體宵禁 除非得到指揮官特別授權
general curfew unless expressly authorized
可以延長工作時間
for extended work hours by unit COs.
有效宵禁時間截止到兩千二百小時
Curfew in effect as of 2200 hours.
所有的加班工作人員 火災警戒員 和值夜班的人
Notice to all late workers, fire watchers and night staff.
整晚都有物品供應
Effective immediately, midnight rations will be served all night.
我們對於七腳怪
Here are some of the many things
還是一無所知
we don't know about heptapods.
希臘語中 Hepta指的是七 Pod指的是腳
Greek. Hepta, "Seven. " Pod, "Foot."
七隻腳 七腳怪
Seven feet. Heptapod.
他們到底是什麼
Who are they?
試圖更加深入的瞭解他們
Trying to answer this in any meaningful way
而現實總是讓人失望
is hampered by the fact that,
在外面 能看見他們的樣子 聽見他們的聲音
outside being able to see them and hear them,
但七腳怪完全沒有留下任何蹤跡
the heptapods leave absolutely no footprint.
對其飛船的化學分析也沒有任何結果
The chemical composition of their spaceship is unknown.
殼體不會產出廢料 不會排出氣體 也沒有輻射
The shell emits no waste, no gas, no radiation.
假設這些殼體之間能夠交流
Assuming that the shells communicate with each other,
卻不被人類所發現
they do so without detection.
殼體之間的空氣不會
The air between the shells is untroubled
受到聲波和光波的影響
by sonic emission or light wave.
那他們是科學家嗎 還是遊客
Are they scientists? Or tourists?
假設他們科學家
If they're scientists,
但並沒有詢問一大堆的問題
they don't seem to ask a lot of questions.
為什麼他們停在了這兒
Why did they park where they did?
世界上最有學識的專家也無法解釋
The world's most decorated experts can't crack that one.
最有可能的原因是
The most plausible theory is
他們選擇停在地球上
that they chose places on Earth
幾乎不會有閃電的地方
with the lowest incidence of lightning strikes.
但是也有例外
But there are exceptions.
另一個可能理論是
The next most plausible theory is that
在1980年 希娜·伊斯頓的歌曲
Sheena Easton had a hit song
在這些地方紅極一時
at each of these sites in 1980.
因此我們還是一無所知
So, we just don't know.
他們是怎樣交流的
How do they communicate?
露易絲在這兒使我們自慚形穢
Here, Louise is putting us all to shame.
取得的第一個突破是
The first breakthrough was
發現了七腳怪所說的話
to discover that there's no correlation
和所寫的字之間沒有任何關聯
between what a heptapod says and what a heptapod writes.
和所有人類文字不同的是
Unlike all written human languages,
他們使用的是意符文字
their writing is semasiographic.
文字代表了意思 但不代表發音
It conveys meaning. It doesn't represent sound.
可能他們覺得我們的文字
Perhaps they view our form of writing
完全是多此一舉
as a wasted opportunity,
母親
行星
生命
男人
星
七腳怪
浪費了一次交流的機會
passing up a second communications channel.
孩子
女人
地球
人類
行走
時間
死亡
系統
科技
太陽系
家
數字
書寫
我們得感謝在巴基斯坦的朋友
We have our friends in Pakistan to thank
對七腳怪文字的研究
for their study of how heptapods write,
因為不像說話 意音文字不會隨著時間改變其意思
because unlike speech, a logogram is free of time.
就像他們的飛船和身體一樣
Like their ship or their bodies,
他們的文字不存在
their written language has no forward
具體的順序
or backward direction.
語言學家稱其為非線性拼寫法
Linguists call this non-linear orthography,
這不由的讓人懷疑 他們也是這麼思考的嗎
which raises the question, "Is this how they think?"
想像一下你要用雙手寫一個句子
Imagine you wanted to write a sentence using two hands,
分別從兩邊開始書寫
starting from either side.
你必須清楚你想要用的每個詞語
You would have to know each word you wanted to use,
和它們所佔據的空間的大小
as well as how much space they would occupy.
七腳怪能毫不費力
A heptapod can write a complex sentence
在兩秒中內寫一個複雜的句子
in two seconds, effortlessly.
而人類要用一個月才做出簡單的回復
It's taken us a month to make the simplest reply.
關於七腳怪如何擴充詞彙
Next, expanding vocabulary.
路易斯認為至少需要一個月
Louise thinks it could easily take another month
才能弄明白
to be ready for that.
嘿
Hey...
你好
Oh, hey.
韋伯在找你
Weber's looking for you.
我知道 不然我為什麼躲在這裏
Yeah, well, why do you think I'm hiding out here?
上來吧
Come on up!
謝謝
Thanks.
這兒真美 對吧
Nice out here, huh?
確實 風景很美
Yeah, it's a nice view.
遠離那些噪音
Away from the noise.
你知道嗎 我剛正好想到你
You know, I was just thinking about you.
你像數學家那樣解決語言問題
You approach language like a mathematician.
我沒猜錯吧
You know that, right?
我就當你在誇我
I will take that as a compliment.
就是在誇你啊
Yeah, well, it is.
當你指導我們繞過那些
As I watch you steer us around these communication traps
我根本沒有察覺的語言陷阱
that I didn't even know existed,
心裏在說 什麼
it's like, "What?"
我猜這就是我單身的原因
I guess that's why I'm single.
相信我 就算你懂得如何溝通
Trust me, you can understand communication
到最後依然還是單身
and still end up single.
我感覺裏面發生的所有事
I feel like everything that happens in there
都要靠我們倆解決了
comes down to the two of us.
那難道不是件好事嗎
Yeah, that's a good thing though, right?
你和我
You and I?
看到每天和我們一起工作的廢柴
Have you seen the jokers that we're working with?
我就在想 幸好還有你
Thank God I've got you!
塞拉利昂
外星人
危機
第25天
英國
拯救我們的種族 !
今晚
Tonight,
第一張外星人的照片在瘋狂傳播
the first photograph of the aliens goes viral.
生物污染是蒙大拿存在的
Biological contamination is a major risk factor
最主要的威脅
at the Montana site.
環保組織如是說
So say environmental pressure groups.
在華盛頓 有80萬人遊行
800,000 march on Washington
抗議政府對危機的處理
to protest the government's handling of the crisis.
接下來會有更多的新聞報道
All this, and more special coverage.
首先和裏面的不明物體進行溝通
First contact with whoever it is that is inside that thing,
猜猜誰在操作這場秀
and who's running the show?
當然是政府
The government.
聽好了 就是那個
That's right, folks, the same government
破壞了我們的醫療保險 搞砸了我們的軍隊的政府
who ruined our healthcare and bankrupted our military.
看看這些人啊
Look at these people!
大多數都是手無寸鐵的老百姓
Most of them don't even have guns!
我們可能會遭遇全面的入侵
We could be facing a full-scale invasion.
我們的總統只是乾等著
Our president's willing to sit back
讓他們大搖大擺地奪走我們的家園
and let them waltz in and take our country.
我們要玩完了啊
We are falling asleep at the wheel, people!
你們知道我沒有胡說八道
You know what I'm talking about. I know you do.
我們現在最應該做的就是
What if the smartest thing we could do right now
展現我們的武力
would be to give them a show of force?
讓他們知道我們的厲害
I'm talking about a shot across the bow.
你認為怎麼樣
What do you think?
第一位來電者 你好
Caller No.1, you're on the air.
發表下你的看法
What do you think?
這個詞是什麼意思
What's this word?
行星
Planet.
就像地球是一個行星
That's, like, um... The Earth is a planet.
想看看我為伽利略老師課上做的東西嗎
Want to see my project for Miss Garriott's class?
當然 小可愛
Yeah, little nose.
我們要自己製作電視節目
We had to make up our own TV show.
如果我們有的話
If we had one.
這兩個人是誰
And who are those two people?
你和爸爸
That's you and Dad.
電視名字叫做
The show is called
和小動物們說話的媽媽和爸爸
"Mommy and Daddy talk to Animals."
哦
Oh!
太可愛了
Well, it's lovely.
好吧
Okay...
呃
Um...
你可以因為爸爸和媽媽的事情而感到不開心
You know it's okay to be sad that your dad and I...
我知道 我沒有
I know. I'm not.
因為我們都很愛你
'Cause we both love you very much.
SSK字幕組
我知道 只是張卡通畫 並不是真的
I know. It's just a cartoon. It's not real.
露易絲
Louise?
你還好嗎
You all right?
我挺好的
Yeah. Yeah, I'm fine.
我也不好怎麼說
I'm not sure it's something I can... I can explain.
你上次去凱特勒醫生那兒檢查是什麼時候
When was your last checkup with Dr. Kettler?
我沒事
I'm okay.
我要去透透氣了
I'm gonna get some air.
-我沒事了 -好吧
- I'm okay. - All right.
我挺好的
I'm fine. Yep.
你怎麼樣
How you feeling?
呃
Um...
我想睡一覺 但我挺好的
I need some sleep, but I'm fine.
好吧
Yeah.
我看過有關這些的
You know, I was doing some reading, um,
書籍
about this idea
裏面說到 如果你沉浸於一門外語中
that if you immerse yourself into a foreign language,
就能重新構建你的大腦
then you can actually rewire your brain.
是薩皮爾沃夫理論
The Sapir-Whorf hypothesis.
對的
Mm-hmm.
這個理論
The theory that, uh...
這個理論說到
It... It's the theory that, uh,
你所說的語言決定了
the language you speak determines
你思維的方式
how you think and...
還會影響你看待事情的態度
Yeah. It affects how you see everything.
這真是
It was, uh...
我很好奇
I'm curious...
你會夢到他們的語言嗎
Are you dreaming in their language?
夢到過幾次 但是
I may have had a few dreams, but I don't...
我不認為那意味著我不能勝任這份工作
I don't think that that makes me unfit to do this job.
你睡過了嗎
Did you sleep?
睡了一會
A little.
你會普通話嗎
Do you know Mandarin?
它在移動
It is shifting.
你將聽到的聲音來自
The voice you're about to hear
中國軍隊的長官
belongs to a Chinese military chief...
尚將軍
General Shang.
帶上吧
Pull it up!
這兒有他和別人說話的衛星錄像
We got a satellite feed here of who he's talking to,
如果你想看看的話
if you want to look.
等下 倒一點
Wait, go back.
停
Stop.
他說這十二個不明物體
He's saying that each of the 12
會提供高科技
is offering advanced technology.
再倒回去 放吧
Go back again. And play.
呃
Um...
我們的科學隊伍正試圖破解密碼
"Our science team is attempting to decode the sets."
密碼 我不知道那是什麼意思
"Sets." I don't know what that means.
一些有利的東西
Something about advantage,
色子 番子 花牌
suits, honor and, uh, flowers.
我不
I don't...
我不知道
I don't know. That's all.
我不知道那什麼意思
I don't know what it means either.
一個小時前 中國調動了軍隊
An hour ago, China mobilized forces.
現在 俄羅斯也緊隨其後
And now, Russia's following suit.
尚要開始搞事情了
Shang's about to start something.
跟著服裝 服裝
Following suit. Suits.
色子 番子 花牌
Suits, honor, flowers...
上校 那些全是麻將裏面的牌
Colonel, those are all tile sets in mah-jongg.
我的天
God, are they...
他們用麻將和七腳怪交流嗎
Are they using a game to converse with their heptapods?
可能 為什麼
Maybe. Why?
打個比方 如果我們教他們下棋 而非英語
Well, let's say that I taught them chess instead of English.
每場對話都可以是一場遊戲
Every conversation would be a game.
每個想法都可以通過對完之後的輸和贏來表達
Every idea expressed through opposition, victory, defeat.
你明白了嗎
You see the problem?
我知道了
Hmm...
如果我只給你一個錘子
If all I ever gave you was a hammer...
那麼所有事都是釘子
Everything's a nail.
我們得問出那個問題了
We need to ask the big question.
準備好了嗎
Ready or not.
我懂了 但在那之間
Yeah, I know, but between there and there.
是時候出發了
Well, it's time to go.
好的
Okay...
七腳怪的目的
Heptapods' purpose.
七腳怪的目的 地球 你們的目的是什麼
Heptapod purpose Earth. What is your purpose?
只有科斯特洛了嗎
Do we only have Costello?
很好 你來了
Okay. There you are.
它說了什麼
What does it say?
提供武器
Offer weapon.
你看見他們寫的了
You saw what they wrote!
他們還沒搞懂那個詞的意思
Using a word they don't fully understand.
-可能只是個要求 -是警告
- Could be a request. - A warning.
夠了 露易絲你說
Enough! Louise?
我們不知道他們是否理解了
We don't know if they understand
武器和工具之間的區別
the difference between a weapon and a tool.
我們的語言和文化一樣複雜
Our language, like our culture, is messy,
有時候 一個詞可能包含很多意思
and sometimes, one can be both.
這是很有可能的
And it's quite possible
他們想要我們提供一些東西
that they're asking us to offer them something,
而不是提供給我們武器
not the other way around.
就好像第一次交易
It's like the first part of a trade.
所以 我們怎樣搞明白
So, how do we clarify their intentions
他們究竟是什麼意思
beyond those two words?
我會再進去一次
Well, I go back in.
就現在 我們進去搞清楚
Right away, we go back in and we clear this up.
聽起來很複雜啊
It's more complicated than that.
這怎麼就很複雜了
How is it more complicated than that?
上校 國防部長
Colonel, the Secretary of Defense
要求和你通話
is on the line for you.
在我們弄清楚它的意思之前
We need to sit on this information
這個消息需要保密
till we know what it means,
所以不要告訴我們的敵人
so we aren't sharing it with our enemies.
還有一種情況是
We must consider the idea
我們的觀光者想要我們自相殘殺
that our visitors are prodding us to fight among ourselves
直到一方取得勝利
until only one faction prevails.
-沒有那樣的事 -就是這樣
- There's no evidence of that. - Sure there is.
多看看歷史書吧
Just grab a history book.
英國人和印度人 德國人和盧旺達人
The British with India, the Germans with Rwanda.
他們甚至在匈牙利命名了
They even got a name for it in Hungary.
不只是一個人掌控著這個世界
Yeah. We're a world with no single leader.
他們不可能只和一個國家做交易
It's impossible to deal with just one of us.
而武器這個詞
And with the word "Weapon" Now...
-哈爾彭 -在 長官
Halpern. Yes, sir!
暫時沒有消息 待命
No confirmation yet. Standing by.
有消息了嗎 他們說了什麼
Anything? What did they say?
中國和俄羅斯都不在線
China and Russia are off the grid.
他們沒和任何人說話
They aren't speaking to anyone.
他們在上次交談中瞭解到的內容把他們嚇壞了
Whatever they learned in their last session has them spooked.
好的 長官
Yes, sir!
上級要求我們離線
We have orders to do the same.
這些是我們的盟友
These are our allies!
你不能這樣
You can't shut us down!
-關閉我們的信號 -快點
- Put us on radio silence. - Do it.
我們收到了來自七腳怪的消息 天啊
We received a message from the hept... Damn it!
我們應該保持溝通
We need to be talking to each other!
你想和他們說話 弄清楚這什麼意思
You want to talk to them? Find out what this means.
基地連線已關閉
Base-camp talk is now offline.
所有的傳譯員和國際聯繫人
All interpreters and international liaisons,
暫時離開 去向協調人報告
stand down and report to unit coordinators.
我們之前從沒有再次對話
We've never re-entered a session before.
露易絲 相信我 我們還有時間
Louise, trust me, okay? We've got time.
我們快成功了對吧
We've just gotta step on it, all right?
使用武器
"Use weapon."
來自外星人的信息
This is the alien message
導致中國政府今天
said to have provoked the Chinese government
讓科學家們退出了
to withdraw their scientists from
國際合作任務
the international mission today.
尚將軍在聲明中說到
In a statement, General Shang said,
中國不再相信外星人了
"China no longer trusts the aliens
他們想要分裂我們
"Who want to divide us.
人類必須相互保護
"Humanity must be protected."
中國請求立即和聯合國進行對話
China has asked for immediate talks at the UN.
阿爾法 19
Alpha-one-niner,
我是禿鷹 完畢
this is Condor, over.
阿爾法19 我是禿鷹 請說話 完畢
Alpha-one-niner, this is Condor, come in. Over.
馬克思上校 禿鷹未收到回復
Captain Marks, Condor not receiving transmission.
收到請回復
Squelch twice if you hear line.
馬克思上校 護送人員被命令
Captain Marks, all escort units
立即停止所有行動
are ordered to cease all activity.
不 不 不 班克斯博士 你不能進去
No, no, no. Dr. Banks, you can't go in there.
我只想問一個問題
I just need to ask one question.
班克斯博士 對話已經結束
Dr. Banks! The session is finished.
你不能 你不能再進去了 裏面非常危險
You can't... You can't go back in. It's dangerous.
聽著 我們只需要五分鐘 不要這麼緊張
Look, we just need five minutes. Don't sweat it.
馬克思 讓他們進去
Marks, let them go.
嘿 艾伯特
Hey, Abbott!
所以 現在是什麼 第37次對話
So, what are we calling this? Session 37?
不 是36次 第二部分
Uh, no, 36, part 2.
為什麼只有他們倆在裏面
Why are they on their own?
我們一直試圖聯繫馬克思上校
We've been attempting to hail Captain Marks.
護送小組並未回復 長官
The escort units are not responding, sir.
為什麼 安排保護人員
Why not? Send security.
提供武器 到底是什麼意思
"Offer weapon, question mark."
你會給我們什麼嗎
Are you offering us something?
科技 設備 還是方法
Technology, apparatus, method?
看 這是一個不同的詞
Yeah, see, this is a different word.
這 這個部分 圖案更複雜
This... This segment, it's a lot busier.
提供科技
Give technology
現在
now.
他在做什麼
What's he doing?
上尉 十點鐘方向
Captain, on your ten.
安保分隊已到 長官
Security detail inbound, sir.
倒計時還剩四分鐘 我們要堅持到底
T-minus 4 minutes remaining. We need to see this through.
好了 沒問題 重新裝彈
Okay, this is it. Lock and load.
我們只需要在結束前拖延住他們
We just need to hold them off until it's done.
收到 只進行示警射擊和鎮壓火力
Copy that. Warning shots and suppressive fire only.
全副武裝 準備掩護
Load up and get to cover.
保持冷靜 我們可以避免人員傷亡
Stay frosty and we can avoid casualties.
艾伯特想讓我寫在玻璃上
Abbott wants me to write on the barrier.
可以這麼做嗎
Can you even do that?
不知道
I don't know.
我沒法同時用兩隻手寫出來
I can't do it with both hands.
露易絲
Louise...
怎麼回事
What is that?
嘿 輕點
Hey! Hey, hey, hey. Take it easy.
你剛剛腦震盪了 躺回去吧
You suffered a concussion. Just lay back.
感覺怎麼樣
How do you feel?
伊恩怎麼樣
How is Ian?
跟你一樣 他沒事
Same as you. He's okay.
誰 呃 誰幹的
Who, um... Who did this?
啊 幾個士兵
Ah, some soldiers.
他們電視看多了
They've been watching too much TV.
什麼聲音
What is that?
別緊張 放輕鬆
Take it easy. Take it easy.
這裏不再安全了 我們在準備撤離
The site's no longer secure. We're standing by to evacuate.
伊恩在哪
Where's Ian?
大概十分鐘前 韋伯把他叫走了
Weber came and got him maybe 10 minutes ago.
直到知道你沒事他才離開
He wouldn't leave until he knew you were okay.
你們整個營裏的工作人員
Your whole tent is on the clock
都在研究你們剛剛的發現
to figure out whatever it is you were given up there.
這是全部嗎
This is all of it?
錄像沒有被爆炸影響嗎
The feed wasn't interrupted by the explosion?
據我所知沒有
Not as far as I can see.
你看到了什麼
You see something?
哦 還未可知
Oh, I don't know yet.
我需要和露易絲的團隊一起研究
I'm gonna need my team to get together with Louise's team.
我需要所有工作人員一起研究
I need everybody working on this.
我們不能離開
We cannot leave.
很高興你醒了
Glad to see you're awake.
我們需要回到裏面 解釋我們不是有意這麼做的
We need to go back in and explain this wasn't our fault.
-我們不能再進去了 -我們必須進去
- We can't go back inside. - We have to.
剛剛裏面發生的是一場襲擊
What happened in there was an attack.
我們可以往好處想
We can hope for the best,
但是我收到命令準備反擊
but I have orders to prepare for retaliation.
我們可能不得不撤離
We may have to evacuate.
不 這才是錯誤的舉動
No, that's the wrong move.
只要他們不走 我們就必須留下
As long as they stay, we have to stay.
他們不是要走
Well, they're not leaving.
為什麼感覺這樣更糟
Why does this feel worse?
中國已經準備進攻
China is on the offensive.
他們正在部署軍隊
They're positioning the military
準備直接把外星飛船轟出大氣層
to blow the alien vessel right out of the sky.
若果真如此
And if this happens,
我們就不能坐以待斃
we can't sit around waiting for retaliation.
所以請全部武裝
So, get prepared.
空軍步兵候命
The Air Force and infantry are standing by.
是 長官
Yes, sir.
突發新聞
今晚 中國將成為首個向外星人宣戰
Tonight, China becomes the first world power
突發新聞
中國發出最後
通牒
的世界強國
to declare war against the aliens.
在聯合國
Following the failure of diplomatic efforts
外交努力失敗後
at the United Nations,
中國已確定其語言專家將於今夜
China has confirmed that its language experts have tonight
在上海發佈最後通牒
delivered an ultimatum at the Shanghai site.
在電視播送聲明中
In a televised statement,
尚將軍 人民解放軍總司令
General Shang, chairman of the People's Liberation Army,
宣稱外星人有二十四小時的時間離開中國領區
said the aliens have 24 hours to leave Chinese territory
否則兵戎相見
or face destruction.
同時尚將軍主張其他國家領導人
And he urged all other world leaders
同中國聯合 統一戰線
to unite with China and take a similar stance.
目前飛船著陸點已集結大量武力
With a huge buildup of forces at their landing sites,
巴基斯坦 俄羅斯及蘇丹都被認為
Pakistan, Russia and Sudan are thought to be
會追隨中國的行動
following China's lead.
肯定不是隨機的
It can't be random.
我們得花費數年的時間了
It's going to take us years.
這個詞是什麼
What's this term here?
媽媽
Mom...
嗯 親愛的
Hmm? Sweetie...
呃 這說的是什麼詞
Uh, what's this term for that thing,
一個專業術語
like a... Like a technical term,
當我們交易的時候
where we make a deal,
我們雙方都能獲益
and we both get something out of it.
妥協
A compromise.
不是
No...
再比如 它是競爭
Like, it's a competition.
嗯哼
Mm-hmm...
最終雙方都很高興
But both sides end up happy.
就像雙贏
Like a win-win.
更學術一點
More science-y than that.
如果你想要更科學的說法 打電話給你爸爸
If you want science, call your father.
謝謝
Thank you.
抱歉
Sorry.
沒關係
It's okay.
我醒了
I'm up.
現在什麼時間
What time is it?
現在是你該打開你一直珍藏的美酒的時候
It's time you opened that bottle you've been hiding.
你是不是有什麼突破
You cracked something, didn't you?
沒錯 過來
Yeah. Come here.
看這部分
Take a look at this section.
他好像在說時間
It seems to be talking about time.
他們的時間符號隨處可見
Their symbol for time is everywhere.
所以這是什麼
So what is this?
一個超光速飛行公式
A formula for faster-than-light travel?
誰說得準
Who can tell?
他們有很多的缺口
There are too many gaps.
沒一個完整的
Nothing's complete.
然後我才恍然大悟
Then it dawned on me.
過來這邊
Come here.
這裏
Right here.
不要只關注存在什麼 還要看看空缺的部分
Stop focusing on the ones. Look at the zeroes.
實物數據佔多少
How much of this is data?
空缺部分佔多少
How much of it is negative space?
所以 我測算了一下
So, I measured it.
0.0833 3循環
0.0833 recurring.
或許你想把它化成一個分數
Perhaps you'd like that as a fraction.
十二分之一
One of twelve.
他們想在這裏說的是這是十二箇中的一個
What they're saying right here is that this is one of 12.
「我們是一個大整體中的一部分」
"We are part of a larger whole."
或者我們是十二個獎品角逐者其中之一
Or we're one of 12 contestants for the prize.
我為什麼要跟他說話
Why do I have to talk to him?
我們都在一起工作
We're all working together.
我們需要和其他地點交流
We need to talk to the other sites,
用他們從七腳怪那裏得到的信息幫助他們
help them with what they've gotten from the heptapods.
我們的通訊被中斷了
We're blacked out.
中國已經揚言要毀掉他們的外星飛船
China just threatened to destroy their shell.
我們只能靠自己
We're on our own.
但是這也說了所有的部分可以拼湊在一起
But this says that all of the pieces fit together.
我要告訴你沒人關心這些
And I'm telling you that no one else cares.
兩小時前
Two hours ago,
我們截獲了一段俄羅斯秘密通訊的音頻
we pulled this audio off a secure channel in Russia.
他們的科研組的一位組員曾試圖傳播出這條訊息
Someone on the science team there was broadcasting wide.
最後一次會議 外星人聲稱
In their final session, the aliens said,
「時間緊迫 合眾為一」
"There is no time. Many become one."
我擔心所有人都開始明火執仗
I fear we have all been given weapons.
如果有人收到這條信息 請
If anyone is receiving this, please...
嗯 我的意思是
Well, I mean,
有很多種方式
there are a lot of ways
可以解釋他說的話
you can interpret what he said.
我不需要一個翻譯告訴我這是什麼意思
I don't need an interpreter to know what this means.
俄羅斯剛剛處決了其中的一個專家
Russia just executed one of their own experts
以防走漏風聲
to keep their secret.
「合眾為一」的意思可能是
"Many become one" Could just be their way of saying
需要各國通力合作
"Some assembly required."
那為什麼只給我們每個國家一部分
Why hand it out to us in pieces?
為什麼不直接給我們完整的
Why not just give it all over?
還有什麼更好的方式能讓我們合作一次
What better way to force us to work together for once?
就算我信你
Even if I did believe you,
你要如何才能讓其他國家馬首是瞻
how in the world are you gonna get anybody else to play along
貢獻出他們的資料
and give up their data?
我們也提供我們的資料
We offer ours in return.
是嗎
Yeah?
做一筆交易
A trade?
這叫非零和博弈
It's a non-zero-sum game.
非零和博弈
Non-zero-sum game.
就是這個 對
That's it. Yeah.
謝謝
Thanks.
有九個著陸地點
Nine of the landing sites have gone
通訊完全中斷
total comms blackout.
唯一聯絡到他們的方式就是長途跋涉
Only way to reach them is to physically drive there
對著邊防戰士大喊 我們正在進行這種方案
and yell at the border guards, which we're doing,
但是這樣太慢了
but it won't be fast enough.
一定有其他方法和他們聯絡
There must be a way to get the message to them.
我們的盟國有希望 但是這樣機會渺茫而且是亡羊補牢
To our allies, maybe, but it's too little too late.
我們現在要做的就是在一國觸發全球戰爭之前
What we need is to get all the other nations online
聯繫到所有可以通訊的國家
before one starts global war.
但是我們現在無法聯繫到他們
And there's no way for us to reach them.
好 等一下 有了
Okay, hold on a second. There is!
它現在處於我們的正上方
It's right above us.
對我們來說它才是當務之急
That's problematic for us right now.
國防部認為這個飛船會報復我們
The Pentagon's convinced our shell will retaliate.
我猜他們會命令我們一個小時內撤離
My guess is they'll order us to evacuate within the hour.
聽著 他們不是我們的敵人
Look, they're not our enemy.
他們並沒有對我們做出攻擊性行為
They've made no act of aggression towards us.
也許這就是他們進攻的方式
Maybe this is their way of being aggressive.
這不是問題
That's not the question.
那什麼才是問題
What is the question?
現在它已經半英里高
How do we get you back in that room
我們怎麼把你們送上去都成問題
when it's half a mile straight up?
我覺得我們在這裏的工作已經結束了
I think our work here is done.
現在決定權在上級手裏
It's in the hands of our superiors now.
她到底在幹什麼
What the hell is she doing?
噢 我的天吶 噢 天吶 不
Oh, my God! Oh, God, no!
科斯特洛
Costello...
艾伯特呢
Where's Abbott?
艾伯特奄奄一息
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我們都很抱歉
We're sorry.
我想要你
I need you to...
我想要你給你們中的其他人發一則信息
I need you to send a message to the other sites.
使用武器
我不
I don't...
我不懂
I don't understand.
你們來這裏的目的是什麼
What is your purpose here?
我們來幫助人類
三千年後
我們需要人類的幫助
你是如何知曉未來
How can you know the future?
我不
I don't...
我不明白 那個孩子是誰
I don't understand. Who is this child?
這部戲叫做
The show is called
《媽媽爸爸和動物對話》
"Mommy and Daddy talk to Animals."
露易絲能預見未來
武器能開啟時間
等一下 不要 等一下
Wait! No! Wait!
-班克斯博士 -露易絲
- Dr. Banks! - Louise!
你還好嗎
Are you all right?
-你還好嗎 -沒事 我沒事
- You all right? - Yeah. I'm all right.
發生了什麼
What happened?
我正在思考 信息量太大了
I'm trying to figure it out. This is too big.
現在不重要了 我們接到命令立即撤退
Doesn't matter now. We have orders to evacuate.
為什麼
Why?
俄羅斯和蘇丹已經和中國統一戰線
Russia and Sudan are following China.
我不明白
I don't understand.
幫我一下 媽媽
Help me, Mama.
露易絲 哇哦
Louise? Whoa!
媽媽
Mom!
Mama!
抱歉 親愛的
Sorry, honey.
今天是周幾 你知道嗎 寶貝
What day is it? Do you know, baby?
星期天
Sunday.
你會像爸爸那樣不要我嗎
Are you gonna leave me like Daddy did?
哦 漢娜 親愛的 爸爸沒有不要你
Oh, Hannah, honey, your daddy didn't leave you.
這個週末你就可以見到他了
You're gonna see him this weekend.
他不再像以前一樣看我了
He doesn't look at me the same way anymore.
是我的錯
It's my fault.
我告訴了他一些他還沒做好心理準備的話
I told him something that he wasn't ready to hear.
是什麼
What?
嗯
Well...
不管你信不信
Believe it or not,
我能預知未來
I know something that's going to happen.
我也無法解釋我怎麼知道 但我就是知道
I can't explain how I know. I just do.
當我告訴你爸爸的時候 他真的很生氣
And when I told your daddy, he got really mad.
她說我做錯了選擇
And he said I made the wrong choice.
是什麼 未來要發生什麼
What? What's going to happen?
這和一種十分罕見的疾病有關
It has to do with a really rare disease.
而且它不可阻擋
And it's unstoppable.
就像你一樣
Kind of like you are,
像你的泳技和你寫的詩
with your swimming and your poetry
以及其他所有你分享給世界的
and all the other amazing things
令人嘆為觀止的事情
that you share with the world.
我所向披靡嗎
I'm unstoppable?
嗯
Yeah.
我扶住你了
I got you.
露易絲 露易絲
Louise? Louise?
我現在才知道為什麼我的丈夫離開我
I just realized why my husband left me.
我的丈夫離開了我
My husband left me.
你結婚了嗎
You were married?
振作起來 我們離開這裏
Come on! Let's get out of here.
媽媽
Mama?
嗯
Yeah?
為什麼我叫漢娜
Why's my name Hannah?
請讓那些人回來
Get those people back, please.
嗯 你的名字很特別
Well, your name is very special,
因為它是一種回文
because it is a palindrome.
順讀和倒讀都一樣
It reads the same forward and backward.
好了 兄弟們 給我搭把手
All right, guys, give me a hand here.
-是 長官 -那個放進包裏
- Yes, sir. - That goes in the bag.
準備出發
Ready to go!
《宇宙語言》
露易絲·班克斯博士著
撤退準備就緒
Evacuation underway.
致漢娜
嘿
Hey...
我們在這裏的任務結束了 這個要帶走
We're done here! We're taking this with us.
七腳怪語言翻譯指南
我能看懂
I can read it.
-我知道這是什麼 -什麼
- I know what it is. - What?
這不是指武器 是說饋贈
It's not a weapon. It's a gift.
武器是他們的語言
The weapon is their language.
他們把它送給了我們 你知道這意味著什麼嗎
They gave it to us. Do you know what that means?
意味著我們可以學習七腳怪的語言 如果我們活下來的話
So we can learn Heptapod. If we survive.
如果你學會了 當你真正學會的時候
If you learn it, when you really learn it,
你就能夠理解他們理解時間的方式
you begin to perceive time the way that they do,
所以你能看到即將發生的事
so you can see what's to come.
但是時間 於他們而言跟我們不同
But time, it isn't the same for them.
時間是非線性的
It's non-linear.
聽著 我們已經盡力了 但是還尚不足以
Look, we did our best, but it wasn't enough.
上尉會接你們上去
The captain will load you up.
你們會在五分鐘後起飛
You're lifting off in 5 minutes.
伊恩 露易絲 很榮幸能與你們共事
Ian, Louise, it was an honor to work with you.
祝你好運
Good luck.
嘿 上校
Hey, Colonel...
我去問一下我們去哪
I'm gonna find out where we're going.
醒醒 媽媽
Wake up, Mommy!
班克斯博士
Dr. Banks...
很高興見到你
A pleasure.
尚將軍 應該是我與有榮焉
General Shang, the pleasure is mine, really.
貴國總統說
Your president said
很榮幸能在此次慶祝會上款待我
he was honored to host me at the celebration...
的確如此
Yeah.
但是我得坦白 我來此的唯一原因
...but I confess, the only reason why I'm here
就是親自會見你
is to meet you in person.
我嗎 真是不勝榮幸 謝謝
Me? Well, I'm flattered. Thank you.
十八個月前
18 months ago,
你做了一件非比尋常的大事
you did something remarkable,
一件即便是我的上級也做不到的事
something not even my superior has done.
那是什麼事
And what's that?
你改變了我的想法
You changed my mind.
你才是此次聯合的根源
You're the reason for this unification,
都是因為你聯繫到了我的私人電話
all because you reached out to me at my private number.
您的私人號碼
Your private number?
尚將軍 我 我不知道您的私人號碼
General, I... I don't know your private number.
現在你知道了
Now you know.
我不強求知道你的大腦如何運作
I do not claim to know how your mind works,
但是我相信對你來說知道號碼一定很重要
but I believe it was important for you to see that.
我給你打了電話 是嗎
I called you, didn't I?
是的 你給我打了電話
Yes, you did.
露易絲
Louise!
好了可以關閉系統了
All right, let's shut down the system.
長官這裏有一個通訊線路正在撥號中國
Sir? There's a sat line here dialing China.
這裏 你說「這裏」是什麼意思
Here? What do you mean "Here"?
拜託 拜託
Come on, come on!
是誰的手機
Whose phone is it?
是你的手機 長官
It's your phone, sir.
立即搜索營地
Search base camp now.
找出是誰在用那部手機
Find out who's using that phone.
盯住那些坐標
And hold on to those coordinates.
是 長官
Yes, sir.
拜託 我要說什麼
Come on... What do I say?
我要說什麼
What do I say?
拜託
Come on.
我永遠都不會忘記你說的話
I will never forget what you said.
你跟我說了我妻子的臨終遺言
You told me my wife's dying words.
找到電話信號源了
We found the source of the phone call.
在淨化室 原地待命
It's in the clean room. We're waiting for instructions.
你在幹什麼
What are you doing?
-你在幹什麼 -改變一個人的想法
- What are you doing? - Changing someone's mind.
-你能幫我爭取二十秒嗎 -這件事上我們無法爭取到時間
- Can you buy me 20 seconds? - We don't have time for this.
不 相信我 幫我爭取二十秒
No, trust me. Buy me 20 seconds.
-你相信我嗎 -好 我信
- Do you trust me? - Okay. Yeah.
班克斯博士 立即放下手機 否則我們就開槍了
Dr. Banks, drop the phone now or we shoot!
放下手機
Drop it!
對不起
I'm sorry!
你是在犯叛國罪
You are committing an act of treason!
-是 -放下手機
- Yes. - Drop it!
結束了 結束了
It's done. I'm done.
十二地著陸點通訊中斷
...blackout from all 12 landing sites
晚上繼續為您播報
continues this evening.
稍等 我們剛收到消息
Hold on, we are just hearing...
我剛被告知切到這則
I'm being told we're going to cut this report
爆炸新聞
to tell you breaking news...
中國正在召開緊急新聞發佈會
...China has called an emergency press conference...
尚將軍
General Shang,
人民解放軍總司令
commander in chief of the People's Liberation Army,
在緊急新聞發佈會中宣佈
has announced in an emergency press conference
中國解除戒備狀態
that China is standing down.
所有已接收情報
...all intelligence they've received
將立即與其它著陸點共享
will be shared immediately with the other landing sites.
來自世界各地的科學家都在篩查
Scientists from around the world are sifting through information
接收自英國 日本
received from the UK, Japan,
塞拉利昂和委內瑞拉的信息
Sierra Leone and Venezuela.
他們獲取自
...the information they have acquired
其境內著陸點的信息
from both of their landing sites...
都證明十二分其一之謎
Also confirming it to be one of the 12 pieces
正在慢慢拼湊成整體
of this puzzle that is being slowly put together.
所以 漢娜
So, Hannah,
這就是你一生的故事開始的地方
this is where your story begins.
他們離開的那天
The day they departed.
你還好嗎
You all right?
儘管知道這次旅程將通往何處
Despite knowing the journey and where it leads,
我還是選擇義無反顧地擁抱它
I embrace it.
且安於迎接這次旅程的每一刻
And I welcome every moment of it.
H-a-n-n-a-h
H-a-n-n-a-h.
再倒過來念 H
Now backward. H...
a-n-n-a-h
...a-n-n-a-h!
漢娜
Hannah!
準備好了嗎 寶貝
You ready, baby?
嗨
Hi!
別擔心 晚安
Don't worry. See you.
爸爸
Daddy!
你還好嗎
You okay?
準備好了嗎
Are you ready?
噢 你猜是什麼 星星的故事
Oh, guess what? Star stuff!
-伊恩 -嗯
- Ian? - Yeah?
如果你能預見自己的一生 從出生到衰亡
If you could see your whole life from start to finish,
你會改變什麼嗎
would you change things?
或許我會說說我經常感受到的
Maybe I'd say what I feel more often.
我 我也不知道
I... I don't know.
你知道嗎 從我開始記事的時候
You know, I've had my head tilted up to the stars
我就經常抬頭仰望星空
for as long as I can remember.
你知道最讓我驚嘆的是什麼嗎
You know what surprised me the most?
不是海底月是天上月
It wasn't meeting them.
而是眼前人是心上人
It was meeting you.
我都忘了被你抱著的感覺有多好
I forgot how good it felt to be held by you.
你想要一個寶寶嗎
You wanna make a baby?
嗯 我想
Yes. Yeah.
SSK字幕組
降   臨
翻譯  REN
翻譯 Dark Paradise
翻譯  yuli
翻譯 Soda
翻譯 Leif
校對 Luke
特效 一隻蠢喵
壓制 黑胡椒
總監 Luke